<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A modest reply humbly offer'd, as an answer to, and confutation of seven arguments collected and deliver'd by Mr. Samuel Lawrence, in a sermon preach'd at his meeting-house in Namptwich, Octob. 16th, 1691, whereby he would shew, that the infants of professing Christians ought to be baptized : with a seasonable word to my brethren of the baptized church / presented by the most unworthiest of her servants, S.A.</title>
            <author>Acton, Samuel, d. 1740?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A452aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43078074</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43078074</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151507</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151507)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2261:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A modest reply humbly offer'd, as an answer to, and confutation of seven arguments collected and deliver'd by Mr. Samuel Lawrence, in a sermon preach'd at his meeting-house in Namptwich, Octob. 16th, 1691, whereby he would shew, that the infants of professing Christians ought to be baptized : with a seasonable word to my brethren of the baptized church / presented by the most unworthiest of her servants, S.A.</title>
                  <author>Acton, Samuel, d. 1740?</author>
                  <author>Lawrence, Samuel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151507:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Modeſt Reply, Humbly Offer'd, As an Anſwer to, and Confutation of Seven ARGUMENTS Collected and Deliver'd by Mr. <hi>Samuel Lawrence,</hi> in a SERMON preach'd at his Meeting-Houſe in <hi>Namptwich, Octob.</hi> 16th, 1691, whereby he would ſhew, That the Infants of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſtians ought to be Baptized: WITH AN APPENDIX OF Seven ARGUMENTS, SHEWING, <hi>That Infants ought not to be Baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A SEASONABLE WORD to my Brethren of the Baptized Church, preſented by the moſt Unworthieſt of her Servants, <hi>S. A.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Coloſſ. 2.8.</hi>
                  </bibl> Beware lest any man ſpoil you through philoſophy and vain deceit, after the traditions of men, after the rudi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents of the world, and not after Christ.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jude 3.</hi>
                  </bibl> Contend earneſtly for the faith, on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> delivered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the ſaints.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for the Author; and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld by <hi>Tho. Pebian,</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Gheapſide,</hi> near <hi>Bread-ſtreet-e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151507:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151507:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL LAWRENCE,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF I am more bold then welcome in the Liberty I take in directing theſe Lines to you, I am ſorry, but muſt be content, and with Patience am reſolv'd to bear the weight of your Cenſure; which I can more eaſily do, then think, that ſuch a Man as you, ſhould with ſuch Fondneſs, upon no better Grounds, and in ſo unuſual a Heat, expreſs yourſelf ſo Unſucceſsfully as neither to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince your Adverſaries, nor Pleaſe your Friends.</p>
            <p>But knowing, with many others, that this comes not with a Surprize upon you, long ſince acquainting you with what is now brought to light, ſhall not ſtand to make any Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, nor for the Author, who never intended the Project of this Undertaking till now, being inform'd of his Death whoſe Pains I had deſir'd, but by the Diſpoſing-Hand of Providence in vain, and therefore have now adventur'd myſelf, believing thro' the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which is moſt ſeen in the Weakneſs of his Creatures, that neceſſary Supplies would be given to ingage in a Cauſe that ſo nearly concerns his Honour and Intereſt in the World.</p>
            <p>Had it not been undue Reflections from the Pulpit, inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Right of my LORD, and impairing, as much as in you lay, the Credit of his Holy Ordinance, together with the Manners of ſome of your Friends, who being preſent when you preach'd that Sermon from the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. and as Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels fill'd with Wind, that muſt either vent or flie, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented within their own Confines, but treſpaſſing upon their Neighbours Borders to proclaim their own Folly, (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſaid together with yours,) boldly affirming, That you
<pb facs="tcp:151507:3"/>
had aſſign'd Scripture enough for Infant-Baptiſm, theſe Lines had never taken Wing.</p>
            <p>But the very act of Providence which brought your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Notes and Bible to my hand, was ſuch as gives ground to conclude, that it was the Divine Pleaſure, the Structure you had built upon ſo ſandy a Bottom, ſhould at once be caſt into the Sea of Confuſion. And to be ſilent, ſeeing his Right is under ſo manifeſt an Invaſion, muſt beſpeak us to be the moſt baſe of Vaſſals; for who is it that is bought with Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of another, from amongſt the Gally-Slaves, to injoy Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but will ever account himſelf oblig'd to maintain his Redeemer's Honour againſt all that ſhall offer to detract from, or lay a Blot upon it: How much leſs then ſhall the Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord be ſtill, who are under a greater Obligation by how much more great the Redemption-Price is, that was given? So that how ever Unfit in myſelf, yet from the Bond I am under, and the Nature of the preſent Exigence, (am forced) with <hi>Creſus</hi> his dumb Son to ſpeak. —Yet from that Reſpect I have always born to you, and ſtill do, I could ſincerely wiſh you were not the Man I have to do with; but ſince it is ſo, I have acted with as much Candour as becomes me, the Nature of the Cauſe conſidered, having not rak'd in the Aſhes of your Reflections, but wiſh they may lie and die, as they ſhall for me, unleſs new ones give life to the old; but hoping better things, and that you will not think the worſe of your own becauſe it brings Intereſt along with it, wiſhing you ſeriouſly to conſider thoſe Words of our Lord, Mat. 5.19. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of the least of theſe commandments, and ſhall teach men ſo, ſhall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven.</hi> And together with <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8, 9. <hi>In vain do they worſhip me, teaching for doctrines the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So in love I commend you to God, and the Word of his Grace which is ſufficient to inſtruct you in all things neceſſary to Salvation, thro' Chriſt, for whom I am all Mens, more eſpecially yours,
<hi>S. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151507:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER. <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> more particularly you who were preſent at the SERMON preach'd from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. by Mr. <hi>Lawrence</hi> at his Meeting-Houſe in <hi>Namp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twich, Octob.</hi> 18. 1691; for whoſe ſakes, next to the Glory of GOD, and our LORD JESUS CHRIST, I have wrote theſe Lines as an Anſwer to his <hi>Seven Arguments,</hi> whereby he would prove, That the Infants of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſtians ought to be Baptized.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>BRETHREN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have reaſon to believe, that you are in good earnest for Salvation, and to ſecure your precious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Souls from Loſs and Ruine, knowing that they once lost ſhall be no more capable of Repair<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Matth. 16.26.</hi> and that its not the whole World, though it could be given by one damned Soul to procure a Change of State; Wherefore, as a learned Man ſaith, <hi>As the Worth and Loſs of Heaven can neither be imagin'd or valued, ſo the dreadful and perpetual Pains of Hell can neither be meaſur'd nor declar'd.</hi> To obtain the one, and eſcape the other (ſure then) ſhould be the principal Deſign and Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of every one of us in this Life.</p>
            <p>The thing is poſſible, and true Happineſs next to GOD's Pardoning Grace in CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S, conſiſts in our Knowledge and Practice; not that Knowledge will profit
<pb facs="tcp:151507:4"/>
other ways then as it is accompanied with Practice: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſays CHRIST, <hi>If ye know theſe things, happy are ye if ye do them,</hi> Joh. <hi>13.17.</hi> Neither will Practice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, but as it is Conformity to that perfect Law and Rule which He hath given us, by which whoſoever orders his Converſation aright, ſhall ſee the Salvation of GOD, <hi>Pſal. 50.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So uſeful is Holy Scripture which GOD hath given us as his Standard to meaſure all things that relate either to Matters of Judgment or Practice by, that without them we are wholly in the Dark, as to the Nature of all Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and Inſtituted Worſhip; as <hi>Solomon</hi> would have been when he was to build the LORD a Houſe, had he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Pattern for his Direction in doing all things that appertained thereto: Now as all things was to be done ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Pattern given of old in the Houſe of GOD, ſo nothing ought to be done now in the Houſe or Worſhip of GOD, but what he hath aſſigned by Pattern and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in his Word: Wherefore ſaith he, <hi>To the law and to the teſtimonies; if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſai. <hi>8.20.</hi> To do more then he hath required, or to do one thing that is not required for another that is, will be found in a Day of Tryal, equally Abominable with a not doing his Require<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at all. It's certain all Perſons and Things ſhall be pronounced good or bad, as they have or have not agreed with this perfect Law of GOD's Word; all Decrees of Councils, all Doctrines of Men, all Controverſies in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, must be brought to the Test, and abide the Award and Determination thereof. Now that I may not detain you here, let me humbly and earneſtly beg three things of you:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>(1.)</hi> That you will paſs Judgment upon what is commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your view in the Arguments for, with the Anſwer and Arguments against Infant-Baptiſm, according as they bear
<pb facs="tcp:151507:4"/>
proportion to GOD's Sacred Word, and not as they accord with far-fetcht Conſequences and doubtful Concluſions, which at best (in Matters of Worſhip) can prove but one uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Medium and forged Warrant, which through the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Induſtry of ſome skilful Artificers is made fatal to many, even ſuch who do either affect Art above Truth, or ſuch who have not skill to diſcern, and ſo become no leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived then certain Country Peaſants in ſome former Troubles in <hi>France,</hi> of whoſe Folly<note n="*" place="margin">Epiſtle to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus.</hi>
               </note> one tell us, <hi>They attempting and entring into a City not far from them, and lighting into an Apothecary's Shop, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht with all kind of Drugs and Dainties, and being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lured by the pleaſant Odours, and delight of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they taſted, and ſuppoſing all to be of the ſame kind, took and ſwallow'd down every thing; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome fell ſick of Feavers, ſome grew Frenzy, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loſt their Lives to pleaſe their Appetites, at leaſt he that ſcap'd beſt gave occaſion of Laughter to the Lookers on.</hi>— What uſe I ſhall make of this ſhall be only to put you in mind, that it is recorded for the eternal Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the noble <hi>Bereans,</hi> That they would not receive any thing, though offered by a <hi>Paul,</hi> until by ſearching the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures they had found whether thoſe things he taught were ſo or no.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>(2.)</hi> In reading of theſe Lines, that you would lay aſide all Prejudice that may poſſeſs your Minds either against the Perſon or Subject, elſe the Mind by it will be rendred utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uncapable of making right Judgment, or receiving Truth though it preſents itſelf with never ſo much Plainneſs and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. Prejudice was one, if not the principal Cauſe why the <hi>Jews</hi> rejected CHRIST.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>(3.)</hi> Having thus diſcharg'd your Minds of what may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Profit, be earnest with GOD in Prayer to help you
<pb facs="tcp:151507:5"/>
rightly to diſcern between the Myſtery of Godlineſs, the Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity that is contain'd and detected in the Scriptures; and then I trust the Plainneſs of Dreſs, in which theſe Lines ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, will not be of conſiderable Diſadvantages to the Truths contain'd therein, for the more falſe any thing is, the more artificially it had need to be ſet off and adorned: A blear'd Eye loves not to look on the Sun. Art and Humane Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence may tickle the Ear, and well-polliſh'd Diſcourſes may affect the Fancy, and yet prove but a mear Sound of Words and empty Husks; remembring it's ſaid of <hi>Lacon,</hi> Hearing a Nightingale ſing, by the briskneſs of its Warbling, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Notes, and the clearneſs and quavering Cadency of its Voyce, judg'd it a good Prey; but when he found and ſaw it to be of ſo ſmall a Size, he diſdainfully left it, and ſaid, <hi>Thou art a Voyce and nothing elſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore where the Evidence of Truth appears, refuſe it not becauſe offer'd in, and preſented under the Diſadvantage of an unpolliſh'd Style, but let the Reaſon of what is ſaid be conſidered.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And that the LORD may give you <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſhall be the Prayer of him that wiſheth you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and eternal Peace from GOD the Father, through our LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, in whom, though the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthiest of his Servants, I am yours,
<hi>S. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151507:5"/>
            <head>A Modeſt Reply, TO M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL LAWRENCE</hi> HIS <hi>Seven Arguments.</hi> FOR Admitting the Infants of Profeſſing Chriſtians into the CHURCH of CHRIST by Baptiſm, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in a SERMON by him preach'd in <hi>Namptwich, Octob.</hi> 18th, 1691.</head>
            <p>AS it may be ſafely concluded, that the great Intereſt of Man's preſent Peace, and eternal Felicity, is emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently concern'd in Religion and Godlineſs, even ſo all true Religion is taught, and takes its Being only from Divine Revelation, which God in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages, and divers manners gave out, until the Knowledge of his Will was moſt perfectly reveal'd in and by his Son, and our Saviour, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. who in Faithfulneſs to his Church diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Truſt committed to him, ceaſing not to make known to the leaſt Jot and Tittle every thing which he receiv'd or heard of the Father, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.15. He alone being found worthy to ſet up a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151507:6"/>
Standard, and to become a Law-giver and Statute-maker unto all Generations, in things partaining to the Worſhip of God; who no ſooner had tranſmitted the Mind of Heaven to the Children of Men, by a ſure and perfect Law, but it paſſes the Royal Aſſent, he fixes the Seal of his own moſt precious Blood unto it for its Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, and then by the Father is advanced to the higheſt Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Glory, as a convincing Evidence not only of his Son's Faithfulneſs, but the Purity and Perfection of that Law which he hath enacted as the only Mediator, to the end Man ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in the whole Will of God.</p>
            <p>And in further Teſtimony thereof, how great hath Heaven's care been throughout all Ages, in preſerving the Scriptures clean from thoſe Corruptions and Errours which the Heart of Man (tho' learn'd, if unſanctied) is too apt to dote on, and cleave unto; it is no leſs then wonderful to conſider in whoſe hands the Sacred Scriptures in paſt Ages have been lodged, and by whom they have been handed down to us, that they have yet ſtrength ſo loudly to bear Witneſs againſt Errours entertained with ſuch Fondneſs, and maintain'd with ſuch Heat as of late hath appeared, particularly in the Defence of that Unſcriptural Practice of Infant Baptiſm; and that there is not yet ſo much as one Word to be produced as their Warrant in doing (what) they have ſo earneſtly contended for, ſtrongly argue, that God hath marvelouſly over-ruled the Heart and Hands of all heretofore concern'd in that bleſſed Work of Tranſlating the Scriptures into a Language known and underſtood by every one of us.</p>
            <p>And as to the Sufficiency of Scripture, as it contains all things neceſſary to be believed, known, or done either for Salvation, or Church Communion: I know not, that what is ſaid in the ſixth Article of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is forreign to the Judgment of any Profeſſing Chriſtian, ſaving thoſe of the Papal Communion, and ſome few of late ſprung up, who through Temptation and the Deluſion of their own Hearts, have rejected the Word as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in the Scriptures of Truth as Uſeleſs; the one accounts it inſufficient to direct us in all things neceſſary, and therefore to the Word they joyn their own Traditions for the rendring it a more compleat and perfect Rule; the other accounts it Uſeleſs, and therefore directs all for Inſtruction to the Dictates of the Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Of both theſe I have only to ſay, (Lord) deliver my Soul from coming into their Secrets.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151507:6"/>But you and we being agreed in all things touching the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Sufficiency of the Scriptures, I preſume from thence an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Freedom in us, to refer the Tryal of the things wherein we differ, to the Determination of Holy Writ, being firmly reſolved for myſelf to abide by its Award, ſincerely deſiring that nothing may paſs for Truth but upon their Teſtimony.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall not take notice of any thing you offer in your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon preach'd from 1 Cor. 7.14. <hi>Elſe were your children unclean; but now are they holy;</hi> before you come to ſtate the Queſtion, (1.) Becauſe I would not have this Paper to ſwell into too great a Bulk. (2.) Becauſe there is not any thing material but what I ſhall meet with under one or other of your Arguments, ſhall therefore recite your Doctrine, which was this:</p>
            <p>Doctrine, <hi>That the Seed of Profeſſing Chriſtians have a Right to Baptiſm, and ought thereby to be admitted into the Church or Body of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether your Text doth preach the ſame Doctrine you do from it, I queſtion, and conclude, that there is no more a-kin between your Queſtion ſtated, and your Words rightly conſider'd in their proper place, then there would have been, had you drawn the ſame Concluſion from the firſt words in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which tells us, That <hi>in the beginning God made the heaven and the earth;</hi> as I truſt hereafter will be made evident to every judicious and unprejudiced Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>You proceed and ſay, <hi>Here I ſhall not undertake to produce all the Proof that is for it, nor anſwer every Quibble that is brought againſt it; but lay that Foundation which if of God ſtandeth ſure, and if it ſtands, the contrary muſt needs fall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> That you have produced more Proof then the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords you for your Practice, is plain; and Scripture-Arguments that ſtrongly make head againſt your Practice, be by you account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Quibbles, is not ſtrange, but very ſtrange it is that you ſee cauſe to query, whether your Foundation be of God, and yet dare lend a hand to ſupport a ſinking and falling <hi>Dagon;</hi> The Idol could not ſtand before the Art, (even ſo Lord) in this our day, let Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour fall before thy Truth; and help you ſo to diſcern the Sandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Foundation upon which all Errour, with that of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm is built, as that you may better improve the Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of its Ruine then thoſe biggotted Prieſts and blind <hi>Philiſtines</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151507:7"/>
did the Fall and Ruine of their adored <hi>Dagon,</hi> 1 Sam. 5.3, 4.</p>
            <p>I now come to your ſeven Arguments you offer as Proof and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, though reaſonably we might have expected for Proof and Confirmation of a Doctrine of ſo great moment, two or three Witneſſes from Holy Scripture; but knowing that no ſuch Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is to be found there, we ſhall (weigh) and allow of your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, provided your Arguments are ſtrongly concluded in, and truly deduced from the Scriptures; and becauſe I would not in the leaſt be thought to injure you in my Reply, I ſhall at large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite your ſeveral Arguments, and ſo well as I can, with the help of ſome Collections, endeavour the Confutation of them. And you ſay in your</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <head>Firſt ARGUMENT,</head>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>(1.)</hi> I argue from the Command of Chriſt, <hi>Matth. 28.19.20.</hi> For <hi>(1.)</hi> the Command is ſo general as to include not exclude Infants, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will be allowed to be a conſiderable Part of the Nations. <hi>(2.)</hi> Chriſt doth here preſcribe the way of gathering his Church, and preſerving it to the end of the World: now his Church conſiſts of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants as well as grown Perſons; and both are to be dealt with accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that State: As to grown Perſons, Firſt teach them and baptize them, as to Infants, finding them Diſciples baptize them in order to their being taught when capable of it. <hi>(3.)</hi> All Nations is ſet in Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Jewiſh Nation; therefore, as the Diſciples would have underſtood what and whom Chriſt meant, if he had ſaid, Go circumciſe all Nations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So, and its obſervable that Baptiſm was of uſe amongſt them, though not a Sacrament before, as <hi>Maimonides</hi> ſpeaks, That they baptized the Infant or little Stranger upon the knowledge of the Houſe of Judgment, <hi>i. e.</hi> on their deſire in behalf of their Children. <hi>(4.)</hi> The Practice of the Apoſtles in Baptiſing whole Houſhoulds, is a plain Comment on the Text, and ſhews how they underſtood it. <hi>Acts 16.15.33. 1 Cor. 1.16. (5.)</hi> Infants are Diſciples, <hi>Acts 15.10.</hi> together with their Parents, therefore may be baptized, if not Diſciples of Man's making; ſo neither was <hi>Paul</hi> yet, of God's making who gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly accepts them, and takes them into his Covenant. If any (object), That ſuch Diſciples are meant as are capable of obſerving Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It's true, as to grown Perſons with whom the Apoſtles had moſt to do, in gathering a Church out of the World to Chriſt, but as the Proſelites were firſt taught and then circumciſed, but there Children
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151507:7"/>
were firſt circumciſed before they were taught, ſo it may and ought to be here nothing in Chriſt's Commiſſion gainſaying it.</p>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>Firſt ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>Whether all that you have ſaid here doth not directly tend to darken Knowledge, I refer to your own Conſcience, and ſhall leave all wiſe men to judge when the Text is read, and the order of it laid down.</p>
                  <p>Our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, after he had declared himſelf inveſted with abſolute Power given him of the Father, to be Soveraign Lord, and ſupream Law-giver to the whole World through all Ge-Generations: He ſaith, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, teaching them to obſerve all things what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I have commanded you: And lo, I am with you alway, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Command is ſo extenſive as authorizes the Apoſtles of our Lord to take in by Baptiſm all Nations Diſcipled, or ſo many of all Nations as ſhould be made Diſciples; but how it includes one Infant, that neither is made, nor is capable (as ſuch) of being made a Diſciple. I ſee not (otherways) than as Infants are a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable part of all Nations, and if therefore to be baptized, then are all Nations to be baptized by the lump, (even) Infidels, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, prophane and abominable perſons, as they are a part, yea, the greateſt part of all Nations: And this will as truly follow as the other, if this Command may be underſtood without reſtriction, but if not, then the limitation muſt needs lye in the Word, which ſays, Teach or (Diſciple); then neither the Infant nor prophane perſon can be admitted by this Text, if the Order in which it is laid down be duly conſidered, which is thus:
<list>
                        <item>(1.) Our Lord Jeſus commands them to (go) to all Nations.</item>
                        <item>(2.) To <hi>teach all Nations,</hi> or Diſciple them.</item>
                        <item>(3.) That they baptize ſuch ſo taught or Diſcipled.</item>
                        <item>(4.) That they ſhall further Teach and Inſtruct ſuch baptized Diſciples to obſerve all other things that <hi>Chriſt hath commanded.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, that this, and no leſs than this, is intended here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear with great Evidence from the Conſent of ſuch as diſſent from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151507:8"/>
us: And therefore Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſpeaking of this Text, ſhews the ſeveral Work and Duty of the Apoſtles, in their ſeveral Places and Orders, who tells us in his ſecond Diſputation of Right to Sacraments, <hi>Pag.</hi> 149, 150<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <q>Their (1.) Task is to make Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which <hi>Mark</hi> calls <hi>Believers.</hi> (2.) Their work is to baptize them, whereunto is annexed the Promiſe of Salvation. (3.) Their work is to teach them all other things which are after to be learned in the School of Chriſt. Further ſaith he, To contemn this Order, is to contemn all Rules of Order; for where can we expect to find it, if not here? I profeſs my Conſcience is fully ſatisfied from this Text, that it is one ſort of Faith, even Saving-Faith, that muſt go before Baptiſm, the profeſſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Miniſter muſt expect.</q> And in his <hi>Poor Man's Family-Book, pag.</hi> 168. ſaith, <q>The Church never knew any Baptiſm, but ſuch as was joyned with a preſent profeſſion of preſent Faith, Repentance, and Renunciation of the Devil, the World, and the Fleſh, and a total devotedneſs to God and Chriſt, with more to this purpoſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the Author of the Annotations began by Mr. <hi>Poole,</hi> upon this Text, expreſly ſaith, <q>I cannot be of their mind, who think perſons may be baptized before they be taught, we want Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of any ſuch Baptiſms in the Scripture, tho' indeed we find Preſidents of perſons baptized, who had but a ſmall degree of knowledge of the Goſpel, but it ſhould ſeem, that they were all taught, and then baptized.</q> Now what this Author ſaith far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with reference to Infant-Baptiſm, becauſe they are a part of all Nations, I leave, as that which may juſtly evidence him guilty of Self-Contradiction and Inconſiſtence.</p>
                  <p>You add further, That <hi>Chriſt is here preſcribing a way to gather his Church, and of preſerving it to the Worlds end;</hi> and <hi>That the Church conſiſts of Infants, as well as grown perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> As to the firſt, we grant, that Chriſt here is preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing a way of gathering his Church, but that his Church was made up of Infants as well as grown perſons, (profeſſing Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers) is a bold Aſſertion, and a meer Impoſition upon your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, having not the leaſt Light or Evidence, nor being able to give ſo much as one Inſtance of any one Infant that was ever ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, by any of the Apoſtles, a Member of any Church by Baptiſm in their days: Could you do this, you would do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to purpoſe; but to undertake this Task would be to labour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151507:8"/>
under an utter Impoſſibility, knowing the old Maxim, that ſays, <hi>That which appears not, is not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You further ſay, <hi>Had Chriſt ſaid, Go circumciſe all Nations, the Diſciples would have underſtood what and whom he meant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It ſeems then, in your Apprehenſion, the Apoſtles were ignorant of what Chriſt meant, and what they did in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance to his Command they did at a venture. Is not this pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Reaſoning, and a manifeſt impeaching Chriſt and his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples? Was Chriſt ſo dark and unintelligible in what he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, that they could not apprehend him? Is not <hi>Go teach and baptize all Nations</hi> as eaſie to be underſtood, as <hi>Go cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe every Male at eight days old?</hi> Surely they did underſtand Chriſt, and you may, if you will not put out your own Eyes, which I entreat you to have a care of, leſt continuing to preach up, and practiſe things contrary too, or at leaſt not agreeable with the Doctrin of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, you become culpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo liable to that Anathema pronounc'd againſt all, tho' an Angel from Heaven that ſhall preach another Goſpel, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. And <hi>Maimonides</hi> tells you no more than what we allow you, That the Jews of old did baptize the Proſelyte and little Stranger, but in that they did not uſe Baptiſm as a Sacrament, as you your ſelf acknowledge, is a Tradition of the ſuperſtitious Jews, an Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſufficient to warrant you in your ſprinkling Infants as a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Ordinance. Sure, Sir, this your Practice, as well as ſome of their Traditions, beſpeaks Chriſt's Command to be void, and of none effect, and in plain terms gives the Lye to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and more, in their <hi>Comments</hi> upon the <hi>Commiſſion of Chriſt:</hi> For Mr. <hi>G. Lawſon,</hi> in his <hi>Magna Charta</hi> dedicated to <hi>Hen.</hi> B. of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, pag.</hi> 27, 28. tells us, That the word <hi>Teach</hi> before baptizing imports a teaching with ſucceſs, ſo as to cauſe the perſons taught to learn, <hi>i. e.</hi> to receive their Doctrin, underſtand it, approve it, be convinced of the Truth of it, and be converted by it, ſo far as to be made Chriſtians. And ſo the Apoſtles underſtood Chriſt, as is evident by their whole practiſe; and if you dare not ſay, that they were miſtaken in the mind of Chriſt, I am ſorry you give me occaſion to tell you, that you are; and as a Friend, I adviſe you to correct the miſtake you are under, and act for time to come more conformably to Chriſt's Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in and his Apoſtles Practice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151507:9"/>But you further urge, <hi>The practice of the Apoſtles in baptizing whole Houſholds, for your practice in baptizing Infants.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> That Houſholds was baptized we grant, but that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants was in thoſe Houſes is more than you can prove, and the beſt ground you have for your Practice here, is Probability; there <hi>may be</hi> and <hi>may not be,</hi> is too ſlight a Ground to build ſo great an Ordinance upon as Baptiſm: We could give you an account of as many Houſholds in this County, if not in this Town, that are baptized, and that have no Children in them, as you read of in the Goſpel; but admit there were Children, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for you to prove, yet it follows not that they were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, it being uſual in Scripture to take a part for the whole; as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.21. ſaith, <hi>All the Houſe went up to offer the yearly Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;</hi> yea, the 22, 23. Verſes ſay expreſly, That <hi>Hannah</hi> and her Child <hi>Samuel</hi> went not up, (yet <hi>all the Houſe.</hi>) So <hi>Luke</hi> 2.1. <hi>In thoſe days went out a decree from Caeſar Auguſtus, that all the world ſhould be taxed;</hi> yet who will underſtand any other part of the World than that within his own Dominions, and within the bounds of his own Territories (yet <hi>all the world.</hi>) And ſo in many other places. But to ſpeak of theſe Houſholds in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, will, if I miſtake not, turn your own Artillery againſt you, which we ſhall do in a few words; and,</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) To the Houſhold of <hi>Lydia.</hi> 'Tis ſaid ſhe and her Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold was baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.15. but no ground to conclude that there were any Infants there, but a fair ground to ſuſpect the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; and that ſhe might be a Maid or a Widow, there being no mention made of her Husband, and ſhe reckon'd the Head of the Family, which is not proper where there is a Husband; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſhe was a Trader, and at this time many miles from home being now at <hi>Philippi,</hi> but was of the City of <hi>Thialira,</hi> as <hi>ver.</hi> 12 compared with the 14. ſo that if ſhe had any Children, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſhe ſhould carry them about with her from place to place, whither ſhe went to trade and merchandize; moſt likely ſhe ſhould leave them at her abode in <hi>Thialira,</hi> and not that ſhe would be cumbered with the trouble and care of her Infants in her Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels to traffick: But that this may iſſue with Evidence againſt you, the Apoſtles, in the laſt Verſe in this Chapter, they went into the Houſe of <hi>Lydia,</hi> and when they had comforted the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, they departed: So that it's plain thoſe of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Houſhold were Brethren, and the Brethren were capable of being comforted, which Infants are not in the ſence of that Text.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151507:9"/>A ſecond Houſhold is that of the Jaylor, in the 33d Verſe of the ſame Chapter, <hi>the Jaylor and all his were baptized ſtraightway;</hi> (all his) that is, as one obſerves, his Wife, his Servants and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, for to them it may more properly refer than to his Children, who whether he had any is uncertain, but whether he had or not, it's not material in this Caſe; for in <hi>v.</hi> 32. 'tis ſaid expreſly, <hi>And they (i. e. Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas) ſpake unto him the word of the Lord, and to all that were in his Houſe;</hi> which cannot be imagined they ſhould do unto Infants: And <hi>v.</hi> 34. ſaith, <hi>He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced believing in God with all his Houſe:</hi> So then all that were baptized in his Houſe, were ſuch as heard the Word of the Lord, and rejoyced believing in God, which Infants are not capable to do. But</p>
                  <p>A Third Houſhold is that of <hi>Criſpus, Acts</hi> 18.8. <hi>And Criſpus the chief ruler of the Synagogue believed on the Lord with all his houſe, and many of the Corinthians hearing, believed, and were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</hi> Though it be certain, that he, with all his Houſe, was baptized, from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.14. yet from this Text it is not ſo plain, that he, with all his Houſe, was baptized, as that he, with all his Houſe, believed on the Lord. And that ſuch as believe were fit Subjects of Baptiſm, who denies? But,</p>
                  <p>A Fourth Houſhold is that of <hi>Stephanas,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.16. ſays <hi>Paul, And I baptized alſo the houſe of Stephanas.</hi> Now, if any enquire what is ſaid of this Houſhold, to hinder but that Infants might be there and conſequently baptized? why enough, and that which may ſatisfie all men, that there were no Infants here; for the Apoſtle ſaith in the 16th Chapter of this Epiſtle, and 15th verſe, <hi>Ye know that the houſe of Stephanas were the firſt-fruits of Achaja, and that they addicted themſelves to the miniſtry of the Saints.</hi> Which Infants, as ſuch, will never be capable of doing, but are to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred unto: Therefore how great an Uncertainty do the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons and Defenders of Infant-Baptiſm labour under! Hence it was that the worthy Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> grants, that no concluding Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument can be deduced from the baptizing whole Houſholds, for baptizing Infants; and certainly the Doctor concludes but ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally herein, knowing that a clear word of Command is neceſſary to conſtitute a Goſpel Ordinance; as you your ſelf have fully ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged in time paſt.</p>
                  <p>I now paſs to the laſt Branch of your <hi>Argument,</hi> wherein you ſay the Infants of Profeſſing Chriſtians ought to be baptized, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are Diſciples, which you would inſinuate from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151507:10"/>
which I find thus worded: <hi>Now therefore why tempt ye God to put a yoke upon the neck of the Diſciples, which neither our Fathers nor we were able to bear.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is here in all this Text to prove Infants Diſciples? Not one tittle; the Diſciples here ſpoken of are thoſe Gentiles that were converted to the Faith at <hi>Antioch,</hi> who met with ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, occaſion'd by ſome that came down from <hi>Judea,</hi> urging the neceſſity of Circumciſion, ſaying as <hi>Verſ.</hi> 1. That <hi>unleſs ye be circumciſed ye cannot be ſaved:</hi> Hereupon <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends with them, and ſays, <hi>Why tempt ye God to put a yoke upon the neck of the Diſciples,</hi> in impoſing the obſervance of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the other Ceremonies of the Law upon the Gentile Church? For the Yoke ſpoken of by the Apoſtle lay not ſtrictly in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, but in keeping of the whole Law, whereunto they were firmly bound and obliged by Circumciſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. which Infants were never capable of doing, neither in the leaſt are here intended; for though this Church at <hi>Antioch</hi> is made up of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, we believe; but that one Infant is here included we deny: For when the Diſſention grew hot between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> and the men that came down from <hi>Judea,</hi> the Diſciples deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to ſend <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> up to the Council at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to enquire as to that matter, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. and in the Third Verſe you read, That the Church or Diſciples ſpoke of in the Second Verſe brought them on their way; and when they returned with their Anſwer from the Council, you read in the 31. <hi>ver.</hi> that <hi>they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced for the conſolation;</hi> and in the 32. <hi>ver.</hi> that <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> exhorted the Brethren, and with many words confirmed them; all which Offices performed, and Comfort received, Infants can no way be capable of, neither can be intended in this place by the Diſciples.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, to ſay Infants, as ſuch are Diſciples, is inſipid, and contrary to the true import of the word, being render'd by all Lexicons and Dictionaries that ever I ſaw, which tell us, that a Diſciple is a Scholar or Learner.<note n="*" place="margin">66 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> to <hi>Dard.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, That thoſe who go about to make Infants Diſciples, do not only loſe their pains, but expoſe themſelves to laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: And though it be true, that all Diſciples are of God's ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and not Man's, as you ſay Infants are, and <hi>Paul</hi> was, yet we tell you, that Infants neither are nor can be made Diſciples without a Miracle, according to the ſence and ſignification of the word; neither are any made ſo, as to be fit Subjects of Baptiſm,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151507:10"/>
till they have been inſtructed by Man what to do; as appears from the Commiſſion and <hi>Paul</hi>'s own Caſe; for, upon his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring what the Lord would have him to do, you read, the Lord ſends him to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>it ſhall be told thee what thou muſt do, Acts</hi> 9.6. And accordingly the Lord ſends <hi>Ananias</hi> to meet and inſtruct <hi>Paul,</hi> as <hi>ver.</hi> 10, 11. I come to your</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>Second ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>I argue from the nature of the Covenant and Baptiſm, as its Seal; the Covenant belongs to them, therefore its Seal, <hi>Gen. 17.7. Acts 2.39. The Promiſe is to you and your Children,</hi> &amp;c. Its true primarily, and principally it belongs to the Parents, who can come in and agree to it, and ſeal, but ſo as to include their Seed: If you have a Leaſe in which your Childrens Lives are put together with your own, will any ſay the Childrens are not in, becauſe the Parents have been the principal Actors? <hi>(1)</hi> So that this is nothing but what is common amongſt Men. <hi>(2)</hi> GOD hath dealt thus with Man all along in the Covenant of Works with <hi>Adam,</hi> in the Old Teſtament with the Patriarchs or Fathers, and can we think He hath altered his Methods? What Evidence can be brought of that? <hi>(3)</hi> It is but reaſon it ſhould be ſo, for Children are a part of their Parents till they come to ſtand on their own Legs, and act for themſelves. <hi>(4)</hi> The thing ſignified doth belong to Infants, as the pardon of Sin, Regeneration, and the Kingdom of Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> therefore the Sign if the greater, then the leſs. If any object, That for the ſame reaſon they may come to the Lord's Table, becauſe they have the thing ſignified; <hi>Anſ.</hi> Weakly argued, becauſe that though the thing ſignified is the ſame, yet the ſign is different, and they may be capable of the one, that are not of the other: Becauſe they receive Milk, are they therefore fit for ſtrong Meat? <hi>(2)</hi> may they not be taken in at the Door, and waſhed by Baptiſm, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe unfit, by reaſon of their Age, to come to the Lord's Supper.</p>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>Second ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>If you would carefully examine and look into the nature of this Covenant mention'd <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. you will find it ſuch as yields not your Infant-Seed the leaſt Right to Goſpel Ordinances, it being a Covenant peculiar to <hi>Abraham,</hi> which God made with him for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151507:11"/>
his natural Seed, his Children according to the Fleſh, wherein we have God promiſing unto him a very numerous and honourable Iſſue, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. (2) That as God hath graciouſly condeſcended to become a God in Covenant to <hi>Abraham,</hi> even ſo He will continue to be the God of his Seed after him, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. from whence it's evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that God hath choſen the whole Off-ſpring of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in a peculiar manner, to be his Covenant-People, by vertue of that Covenant that He made with him for himſelf and his Seed; and therefore (3) God on his part promiſeth to plant and ſettle the Seed and Poſterity of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the promiſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> which was a Bleſſing peculiar to that People, made ſure to them by a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-promiſe on God's part, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. as a Token whereof, he gives them Circumciſion to be kept and obſerved by them, through their Generations, as <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. And this we judge eaſie to make evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, were that our Buſineſs, though there be ſomething of the Covenant of Grace intermixt with it.</p>
                  <p>But if by <hi>Covenant, Gen.</hi> 17.7. you mean the Covenant of Grace made in Chriſt, the alone Mediator unto Eternal Salvation, why then we cheerfully aſſent, that the Children of all profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are included, and heartily believe that the Infants of others are not excluded, this Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> being but a reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of that which God made with lapſed <hi>Adam,</hi> which was the Covenant of Grace in the firſt Edition of it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                  <p>And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is ſo far from thinking that any are excluded the Grace of this Covenant, that he affirms, The Law of Grace was as truly made with all men in <hi>Adam,</hi> as the Law of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency was; and that all were really alike in <hi>Adam;</hi> and that <hi>Cain</hi> was not the Serpents Seed meerly for original Sin, and as born of <hi>Adam,</hi> as <hi>Abel</hi> was; nor did God make him the Serpents Seed by Reprobation, but that he made himſelf ſo by ſuperadded Sins againſt the Redeemer and Law of Grace.</p>
                  <p>So that if a being in the Covenant of Grace be a ſufficient ground to baptize any, why then it is confeſt, that all Infants have equally a Right to Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>But it is humbly offer'd, That neither Baptiſm now, nor Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion in its place, was given as a Sign and Seal to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace; for though the efficacy of its Grace did reach in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents and Believers in all Ages, yet what Ordinance was ever annexed to it as its Seal through the ſeveral Ages from <hi>Adam</hi> to <hi>Noah,</hi> in which Ages lived <hi>Abel, Seth, Enoch,</hi> who by Faith wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with God, and <hi>Noah,</hi> with whom this Covenant was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151507:11"/>
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.18. and from <hi>Noah</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and from the time that <hi>Abraham</hi> had this Covenant ratified by a ſure Promiſe of a faithful Seed, before the Covenant of Circumciſion was given out, which was about 25 years.</p>
                  <p>A Seal it was to <hi>Abraham</hi> of the Righteouſneſs of his Faith wherewith he believed whilſt uncircumciſed; ſo the Holy Ghoſt applies it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.9, 10, 11. Verſes, but to no other Perſon as a Seal as I know of. Nay, to imagine that Circumciſion was a Seal proper and peculiar to the Covenant of Grace, muſt needs be a Miſtake, elſe the Patriarchs of old, <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> King of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and Prieſt of the Moſt High God, an eminent Type of Chriſt, juſt <hi>Lot,</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> God's righteous Servant, of whom it's ſaid <hi>there is none like him in all the Earth,</hi> could have laid as good a claim thereunto as any beſides; but Circumciſion never received its Being as a Seal annexed to the Covenant of Grace, for had it been given as a Token peculiar thereto, it would have remain'd (I preſume) as unchangeable as the Covenant itſelf, and would not have vaniſh'd away with the other ſhadows of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Diſpenſation. So that though we grant your Infant-Seed to be in the Covenant of Grace, yet becauſe of their Intereſt therein, it follows not that they have a Right to Baptiſm, that being now no more a Sign peculiar to the Covenant, than Circumciſion was, that is now aboliſh'd; for were it a Sign, then the Covenant once had two Signs annexed to it, as proper and peculiar, even from the time of the inſtitution of Baptiſm to Chriſt's Death; till then Circumciſion was in force, and how abſurd is this to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine? Neither is Baptiſm any more a Sign which you grant Children than the Lord's Supper, of which you moſt uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deprive them, for they who in a Goſpel ſence have a Right to the one, have no leſs Right to the other.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, the Seed promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the Covenant of Grace made or renewed with him, is a ſpiritual and believing Seed; and ſo the Holy Ghoſt expreſly tells you, if you dare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon his Teſtimony, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9. of whom <hi>Iſaac</hi> was the Type, not a carnal and fleſhly Seed, figured by <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> as is obvious in the Allegory explain'd by the Apoſtle <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. from 22, to 29. And as it is Faith only which denominates a perſon to be the Child of <hi>Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.7, 9. ſo it is Faith only that beſpeaks a Perſon to be a fit ſubject for Baptiſm, as <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37, 38. Could any perſon ſhew where the Holy Ghoſt calls Baptiſm a Seal, 'twould be of ſome ſervice to your Cauſe, but as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151507:12"/>
that cannot be aſſigned, ſo Baptiſm cannot be any more than Circumciſion was, a Seal; for the proper uſe of a Seal is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, ratifie, and make ſure Bonds and Contracts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But, I pray, what is it that Baptiſm confirms, ratifies, and makes ſure unto Children, more than what is through Grace made ſure to them, to wit, Eternal Life by Jeſus Chriſt without Baptiſm? 'Tis true, by Faith in Baptiſm we put to our Seal, but there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe which God annexeth as his Seal, whereby he ſealeth up Believers, the alone Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and confirms them in the ſure hope and expectation of Eternal Life, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Holy Spirit, Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Grieve not the Holy Spirit of God, whereby you are ſealed to the day of Redemption.</hi> Many may be baptized, that are not of the Seed promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as many ſuch heretofore have been to inſtance only in <hi>Judas, Simon Magus</hi> and the fooliſh Virgins, but the Holy Spirit is given to none as a Seal, but ſuch who by believing are not Baſtards, but the true Sons of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore, if you conſider the nature and ſcope of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> it muſt needs make void your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of arguing, becauſe it's ſaid to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſay you to us and our ſeed.</hi> But now conſider, are each of you by this Covenant made the Father of a bleſſed Seed, as <hi>Abraham</hi> was the Father of the Faithful? Or can you claim the Promiſe for your ſelves and your Seed, according to the Tenure of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Covenant, and as he might <hi>(know)</hi> but we muſt reſt in a relation to him, as Children, and ſo receive his Bleſſings, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Bleſſings promiſed to him for his Seed, and that by means of our own Faith, and for our ſelves alone? Believers, becauſe they are <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, are <hi>bleſſed with faithful Abraham, Gal.</hi> 3.9. <hi>And if we are Chriſt's, then are we Abraham's ſeed and heirs according to promiſe, ver.</hi> 29. So much to the Covenant and its Seal.</p>
                  <p>You add, <hi>The Promiſe is to you and your Children Acts</hi> 2.39.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> If by Promiſe you mean the Remiſſion of Sin, and the Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, ſpoken of in <hi>v.</hi> 38. we are of your mind, That they belong to every penitent and believing Jew: Even ſo to every penitent and believing Gentile, the Wall of Partition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now taken down, is this Grace extended, as is plain in the cloſe of the Verſe, <hi>Even to as many, (i. e.</hi> Jews or Gentiles) <hi>as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> But doth it follow hence, that any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be baptized before Repentance, whereas it is our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151507:12"/>
being renewed by Repentance and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that evidenceth our Right to the Grace promiſed, and Baptiſm is preſcribed to be performed as a Duty by ſuch, for the obtaining the Grace promiſed? But if you ſay it doth follow, I demand why <hi>John</hi> did treat any of the natural Offspring of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſo roughly as he ſeems to do, calling them a Brood of Vipers, and as ſuch, rejected them, requiring them to bring forth <hi>Fruits meet for Repentance, Mat.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. And doth not <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. as plainly ſay, <hi>Repent and be baptized?</hi> Is not therefore to baptize any without the leaſt ſhew of Repentance in the Subject, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the Order of the Holy Ghoſt, it being certain, that <hi>you and your Children,</hi> in the 39th Verſe, is not ſo properly you and your Infant, as you and your Poſterity? I wiſh it were not to be ſaid of you in this caſe as <hi>Stephen</hi> ſpeaks of ſome Jews in another, <hi>Ye ſtiff-necked and uncircumciſed in heart and ears, ye do always reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt; as your Fathers did, ſo do ye, Acts</hi> 7.51.</p>
                  <p>You proceed, telling us, <hi>That God dealt thus with Man in all Ages, in the Covenant of Works with</hi> Adam, <hi>in the Old Teſtament with the Patriarchs or Fathers, and can we think He hath altered his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods? What Evidence of that?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the Tranſactions of God with his People and their Seed in all Ages, hath been in a Covenant-way, and will be ſo to the end of the World, and that our Seed is intereſted in the Grace of the ſame Covenant that <hi>Adam</hi> and the Fathers were in all Generations; God hath not altered his methods at all, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Covenant he hath made, which is unalterable and everlaſting as <hi>David</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. As you had an Intereſt in the Covenant of Grace, ſo have your Infant-ſeed, but ſhould they live to forfeit their Intereſt in that Grace by actual Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, as you and I have done, may not God direct to the uſe of ſuch <hi>Mediums</hi> as Faith, Repentance, and Obedience are, for the Sinner's Recovery, and give out ſuch Laws and Ordinances as is conſiſtent with his own Grace and Wiſdom, upon his diſſolving of one Church Frame, and erecting another, without the Sinner's controul?</p>
                  <p>You ſay, <hi>Children are a part of their Parents, and of the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition with them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> If this paſs for right Reaſon with you, it will not ſo with me, neither will it at another turn paſs for good ſence with you. We grant, that Children are of the ſame nature (humane)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151507:13"/>
with their Parents, Bone of their Bone, and Fleſh of their Fleſh, but not alwaies of the ſame ſtate with their Parents. What think you? Was <hi>Cain</hi> of the ſame Condition with <hi>Adam, Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> with <hi>Abraham, Eſau</hi> with <hi>Iſaac, Abſalom</hi> with <hi>David, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> and <hi>Amon</hi> with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> or good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> with wicked <hi>Ahaz,</hi> or good <hi>Joſiah</hi> with his wicked Father <hi>Amon,</hi> or thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who enter'd and poſſeſſed the promiſed <hi>Canaan</hi> with their wicked Father, whoſe Carcaſſes for their Sin fell in the Wilderneſs. How directly oppoſite is this your beloved Notion to that Rule of perfect Righteouſneſs and Equity, which God hath laid down in that 18th of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> wherein he atteſteth, that <hi>all Souls are his,</hi> as <hi>v.</hi> 4. and that <hi>the ſoul of the Son ſhall not dye for the ſin of the Father;</hi> intimating, that the Father by becoming a wicked Apoſtate and abominable Idolater, may change his own State, and forfeit his own Intereſt in the Covenant, but thereby ſhall not weaken his Childs Intereſt in the Covenant, which abideth firm unto Eternal Life, notwithſtanding any Sin in the Father; nothing can ruin that, but the Childs own Diſobedience, as the whole Chapter ſheweth.</p>
                  <p>Nay, if the good and happy eſtate of Infants depends ſo much upon the believing of mediate Parents, is not the Salvation of ſuch Infants rather to be imputed to their Parents believing, than to Chriſt in dying? But this your way is not God's way, for God claims a Right to, and a Propriety in the Children of an Apoſtate <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> as well as the Children of his faithful Servants; which could not be, ſhould the Covenant-Intereſt of Children be ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the defection of their immediate Parents; but ſo it is, <hi>Ezek</hi> 16.20, 21. <hi>Moreover, thou haſt taken thy ſons and thy daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, whom thou haſt born unto me, and theſe haſt thou ſacrificed unto them, to be devoured: Is this of thy whoredoms a ſmall matter, that thou haſt ſlain my Children?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You add, <hi>That the thing ſignified belongs unto Children, to wit, Pardon, Regeneration, and the Kingdom of Heaven, if the greater, then the leſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That the Grace of Pardon belongs to Children we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, flowing purely from the Grace of God in Chriſt to them, and not by vertue of any Act of Faith in their immediate Parents; That the Kingdom of Heaven alſo belongs to Children, we fully conſent to with you; but that Regeneration doth belong to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or the Duties of it is any where required of them, I profeſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151507:13"/>
my ſelf a Stranger; and that this may iſſue, I do ſincerely promiſe, that when you can by good warrant prove it the Duty of Infants to be regenerated, and that ſuch are regenerated, according to the true ſence of that word, to be one with you in the baptizing of them.</p>
                  <p>As to the Objection formed in the cloſe of your Argument, I judge it ſtands ſtrong againſt you, till you have given us a more convincing Anſwer, than telling us it's weakly argued, amounts to, appealing to your own Conſcience, whether Infants, with reſpect to Spirituals, are any more fit for Milk than ſtrong Meat, whilſt capable of neither; and whether the Prerequiſites neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to Baptiſm be not ſuperiour to the Capacity of Children, as thoſe neceſſary to the Lord's Supper, whether an actual Dying to Sin can be any more the work of an Infant than Self-examination. I now come to your</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <head>Third ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>I argue from Circumciſion; Baptiſm comes in the room of Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Col. 2.11, 12.</hi> they belong to the ſame Covenant, they have the ſame Nature, the ſame Ends and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes; there is no eſſential Difference, therefore there is the ſame reaſon why Children ſhould be baptized now, as that they ſhould be circumciſed then; and had it not been ſo, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the believing Jews would have made a ſcruple of it, and debated with the Apoſtles about it, as they do of other matters, and that would have occaſion'd a more full Deciſion of the Point; but there was no occaſion given them to raiſe Scruples, and therefore we hear no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it. <hi>[Objection.]</hi> But there is no Command. <hi>[Anſw.]</hi> A general Command there is for the making it an Ordinance, a particular Command there did not need, as to the determining the proper Subjects of it, becauſe it is what might eaſily be gathered from the foregoing practice of the Church: And that there is no particular Command, is an Argument to me, that though Chriſt changed the outward Signs, yet not the Subjects, for if it had been ſo, he would have told us. And that there is no little weight in theſe three Scripture-Arguments, and over, that which is equivalent to an expreſs Command.— <hi>I ſpake to wiſe men, judge ye what I ſay, 1</hi> Cor. <hi>10.15.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151507:14"/>
                  <head>Third ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>If Circumciſion be the beſt Authority you have for Infant-Baptiſm, as I think it may be, or at leaſt as good as any, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Caſe, I ſhould mightily pity you, to think how poor a ſhift you make to prove a New-Teſtament-Ordinance by an Old-Teſtament-Writ, and an aboliſh'd Ceremony. Is not this as good Arguing? The Lord's Supper comes in the room of the Paſſover; the Children eat of the Paſſover, why not of the Lord's Supper? But that Baptiſm comes in the room of Circumciſion is not in the leaſt proved, nor can be from <hi>Col.</hi> 2.11, 12. for there the Apoſtle is ſpeaking of a Circumciſion, then and to this day in force, to wit, the cutting of the fore-skin of the Heart, a putting off the Body of Sin, in token whereof the believing <hi>Coloſſians</hi> are ſaid to be buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, that Baptiſm comes not in the room of Circumciſion, is further evident, as they were both in force together, from the time of Baptiſms inſtitution to the end of our Saviour's Life; whereas if Circumciſion had been a Type of Baptiſm, the Shadow muſt have vaniſh'd when the Subſtance was come, but no man will ſay, that Circumciſion was aboliſh'd, until Chriſt by Death nail'd it, with other Ordinances that was againſt us to his Croſs.</p>
                  <p>You add, <hi>They belong to the ſame Covenant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That they may appertain to the Covenant, as annexed thereto by poſitive Inſtitution, we believe but as we told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neither of them as Signs and Tokens proper and peculiar to the Covenant of Grace, and therefore can belong only to them to whom they are aſſigned.—</p>
                  <p>You ſay, <hi>They are of the ſame nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Is not this to ſay the Miniſtration of Chriſt is as legal as the <hi>Moſaical,</hi> contrary to <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6, 7. and ſo on. If Fleſh and Spirit, Legal and Evangelical, be one in Nature, then Baptiſm is the ſame with Circumciſion.</p>
                  <p>You add further, <hi>They have the ſame Ends and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> How that appears I know not: Was not this one end of Circumciſion, to confirm unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Jews, in their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Generations, that Chriſt the Promiſed Seed ſhould come of the Line of <hi>Abraham,</hi> according to the Fleſh; whereas Baptiſm hath no ſuch End, therefore the Analogy betwixt them are not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151507:14"/>
the ſame as you imagine: However from what you have ſaid you conclude, there is the ſame Reaſon that Children ſhould be baptized now as circumciſed then, if you have the ſame warrant for the one as for the other: I confeſs, the Reaſon is the ſame, elſe not; for the tryal hereof, I will briefly enquire (1.) what it was that made Circumciſion the Duty of Children; (2.) the Qualifications that gave Children a Right thereunto. But,</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) That which made Circumciſion the Duty of Children, was not their Covenant-Intereſt, as we have before ſhewed. Had that, the Patriarchs, <hi>Melchiſedeck, Lot,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> had had an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right thereto, and their Poſterity, as they were of the ſame condition with them, as before you have argued; but it was the poſitive Command of God, given out to <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10. <hi>Every Man-child amongſt you,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>ſhall be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</hi> Here Circumciſion is introduced by Divine Inſtitution and Appointment; and that you may aſſuredly know who are the Subjects hereof, the Lord plainly tells them, <hi>every male Child amongſt</hi> them <hi>ſhall be circumciſed,</hi> the time when is expreſly ſet down, <hi>viz. at eight days old, v.</hi> 12. They were not to do it ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor deferr it longer. And as the Law is thus expreſs for the Male Children, through their Generations, even ſo it is as poſitive for thoſe born in their Houſes, that are not of their Seed, and the Stranger that is bought with their Money, <hi>v.</hi> 13. and alſo for the Proſelyte, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48, 49. And to oblige all to the due obſervance of this Law, the Lord joyns a ſevere Threatning of diſinheriting or cutting off every uncircumciſed Male Child amongſt them, (or rather every man amongſt them that circumciſed not his Males) elſe the Commination would turn its edge againſt the Child for the Parents Fault, knowing the Child could only be paſſive in the thing. Thus you ſee by what Authority Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was practiſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) The Qualification that gave Children a Right thereto, was not their Covenant-Intereſt, for then their Females had the ſame Right as their Males; beſides, by vertue of the Inſtitution, ſuch were to receive Circumciſion, as you will have much ado to believe were intereſted in the Covenant, to inſtance only in <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> and the words of the Apoſtle, that ſaith, <hi>All are not Iſrael that are of Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham</hi>'s whole Male natural Seed muſt needs be circumciſed; yet who will imagine, that the numerous Iſſue proceeding from him were ſo intereſted in the Covenant, as <hi>Abraham</hi> and the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151507:15"/>
were, neither was any thing of Duty required as a neceſſary Prerequiſite to qualifie <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed for Circumciſion, more than a deſcending lineally from him; a being his Children ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Fleſh, qualified them for, and intereſted them in the Bleſſing of the Covenant of Circumciſion, which are inferior to the Bleſſings of the new Covenant and Goſpel Miniſtration: So that it's evident the carnal Seed of Believers can obtain no greater Priviledge, than the Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> did by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion, whoſe Priviledge reached not to an Intereſt in Goſpel-Bleſſings (or the New Covenant) unleſs they had obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that Right for themſelves by believing, otherwiſe, as one ſaith well, they had no more Right to them by their natural deſcent from <hi>Abraham,</hi> than <hi>Iſhmael</hi> had in their Covenant of Peculia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
                  <p>And as of old Circumciſion was not to be adminiſtred to any but thoſe appointed by the expreſs Will and poſitive Law of God; neither ought Baptiſm now; nor can any man conclude from a good ground for Infant-Baptiſm, till as good Authority be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced for it, as they had of old for circumciſing the Males of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You add further, <hi>Doubtleſs if it had not been ſo, the believing Jews would have debated with the Apoſtles about it, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> I confeſs, had they not learned better Manners, and been of much a better Temper than many in our days, they would not only have debated but quarreled with them, as ſome do, thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away Truth as a Troubler of their Coaſts, as the <hi>Gadarenes</hi> did Chriſt; but the Believers of old learned Chriſt to <hi>better ends,</hi> than to maintain unneceſſary Debates with the Apoſtles, being ſatisfied from the nature of the Goſpel Miniſtration, that there was no room for Controverſies in Chriſt's changing the Subject as well as the Ceremony; and you may ſee that Point as fully decided and reſolved as they did, would you rid your mind of Prejudice, and with a ſingle Eye look into the Commiſſion where Chriſt bids them to <hi>make Diſciples and baptize them,</hi> and into the general Practice of the Apoſtles, which did perfectly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpond with the Command, which Command was made the Rule of their Proceedings, and not the demoliſh'd form of the Jewiſh Church: And Chriſt, in faithfulneſs to his Church, and in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to little Infants, hath as evidently changed the Subject as the Sign, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16. which in conjunction with the general Practice of the Apoſtles, in that they never baptized one Infant,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151507:15"/>
puts the thing out of doubt. Thus, I hope, your three topping Arguments are fully anſwered, which you ſay are equivolent to an expreſs Command; an Aſſertion ſo impudent, that I pray God it may not be laid to your Charge; for there is not any thing ſaid in all of them, but what may beſpeak you to need, that ſome one teach you which be the <hi>firſt Principles of the Oracles of God,</hi> Hebr. 5.12.</p>
                  <p>And now Brethren, I hope, as wiſe men, you will judge, and ſeriouſly conſider what is ſaid, <hi>and the Lord give you underſtanding in all things,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.7. I now come to your Argument of leſſer magnitude.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>Fourth ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>Little Children belong to the Kingdom of Heaven, therefore are of the Church, and ought not to be excluded, but admitted by Baptiſm, <hi>Matth. 19.14.</hi> They, how little ſoever, have an intereſt in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of the Goſpel Diſpenſation, as well as they had under the Law formerly, and accordingly are as capable of Eternal Bleſſedneſs in Heaven, and the ſame Objections lye againſt their being ſaved, as againſt their being baptized, <hi>viz.</hi> That they cannot actually believe, <hi>Mark 16.16.</hi> If any object, Chriſt means Children in Humility, not in Age, as he doth <hi>Matth. 18.2, 3. Anſwer,</hi> That cannot be ſo underſtood here; becauſe he here ſpeaks of ſuch as were brought unto him, and he took into his Arms. Beſides, it would not then be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient ground for the check he gives his Diſciples. <hi>(Objection).</hi> But he did not baptize them. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> We do not know that he baptized any. He did that which was greater, and that which makes them qualified Subjects for Baptiſm; for grant to them a Church Relation, and Baptiſm will follow upon it; if one ſtands good, the other will; and that is what we plead for from this Text.</p>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <head>Fourth ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>That little Children, as ſuch, belong unto the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we diſcent not from you one jot in this Truth; for ſince Chriſt hath ſaid, that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> we joyfully and ſtedfaſtly believe the certainty of it, and that little Children are of the Church of God, <hi>i e.</hi> the Univerſal and Inviſible Church, which contains all the Elect of God, known and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151507:16"/>
known unto us, and that to the moſt remote Corners of the Earth, in which bleſſed ſtate they abide, though their Parents may ſuffer a change of ſtate by ſin, yet that alters not the ſtate of Children, nor nothing can, till by their voluntary departure from God in chooſing ſinful ways, they deſtroy themſelves. To prove Infants (as ſuch) in a viſible ſtate of Salvation, we conceive not difficult, the words of Chriſt ſtrongly concluding it.</p>
                  <p>But if by Church you mean the viſible Church of Chriſt, and do ſay, That becauſe little Children are of the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that therefore they are of the viſible Church, as that moſt be intended, becauſe of your pleading for admiſſion for them, then I conceive your Concluſion to be moſt untrue. (1.) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, to ſay the Fleſhly Seed of Believers are born within the Pale, and Members of the Church of Chriſt, is a Doctrine For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to that of the Goſpel. (2.) Becauſe ſuch a Doctrine, in a great meaſure, deſtroys the right end of Baptiſm, which is to make them Members of it, that are not, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. and 47. and not to bring them into the Church, that are in it already. (3.) Becauſe Infants, as ſuch, are not capable, and fit matter to make right Members of the Church of Chriſt under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel: For, ſays the Apoſtle writing to Church Members, <hi>Ye alſo as lively Stones, are built up a Spiritual Houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices acceptable to God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. which Infants can neither be nor do. (4.) To ſay Infants are Members of the viſible Church, is incongruous to all Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that ever I met with of a Goſpel Church, as I might ſhew by ſome of your own. I forbear to name ours, as that which may not paſs with you for currant, therefore ſhall aſſign only that of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as an Evidence againſt you, which ſpeaks in the Nineteenth Article, as follows:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The viſible Church of Chriſt is a Congregation of faithful Men, in the which the pure Word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly adminiſtred according to Chriſt's Ordinance, in all thoſe things that of neceſſity are requiſite to the ſame.</hi>—which ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſpeaks the Church of Chriſt to be excluſive of Infants.</p>
                  <p>Further, your grant that Children before Baptiſm belong to the Kingdom of Heaven doth call into queſtion that part of the Church Catechiſm which teacheth her Catticuminies to ſay,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151507:16"/>
That in their Baptiſm they were made <hi>Members of Chriſt, Children of God and Inheritors,</hi> or <hi>(Heirs) of the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> and if they are Members of the Church, as you confeſs, they belong to the Kingdom of Heaven, is not your own practice as forreign; when as, in your baptizing any, do tell the People that thereby that Child becomes a Member of the Church of God; a goodly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour you do 'em indeed by Baptiſm, you make them what it ſeems they were before, and no more by your own Grant.—</p>
                  <p>Again; That your Concluſion is not true, that ſaith, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe little Children are of the Kingdom of Heaven, therefore they are of the Church, and ought to be admitted by Baptiſm, is further evident, in that there are many that ſhall be ſaved, as have not the leaſt ſhew of Right to a Place in, and to the Priviledges of the Church of Chriſt, of which Infants are ſome who have not fin'd actually againſt the Law of Nature; and the reſt are thoſe Heathens who do live and walk up to that Light and Law of Nature which God hath placed in them, who are not bleſt with the Goſpel Light, nor any Divine Revelation, over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Light of Natural Conſcience: and ſurely ſome ſuch there may be, of whom the Apoſtle ſpeaks <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14. <hi>who do by Nature the things contain'd in the Law;</hi> and with reference to ſuch, in all probability, Chriſt ſpake, ſaying, <hi>Many ſhall come from the Eaſt, and from the Weſt,</hi> meaning the moſt remote parts of the Earth, <hi>and ſhall ſit down with</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Jacob <hi>in the Kingdom of Heaven; but the Children of the Kingdom ſhall be caſt out,</hi> Matth. 8.11, 12. If it be granted that there may be any ſuch, it's evident the Kingdom of Heaven will be a Receptacle for them; but who in the leaſt can imagine that they have any right to Goſpel Priviledges? ſo that your Concluſion muſt needs fall. A right to Heaven from this Text is granted them, but it yields them not the leaſt Evidence of a Right to a Church Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and Priviledge. So that I conceive all your pains in plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from this Text vain, and in all that you have ſaid, to be but like one that beateth the Air. A gallant Vapour, brandiſhing a Sword that hath no Enemy to ſtrike at, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſay the ſame Objections lye againſt their being ſaved, as againſt their being baptized, if they cannot actually believe</hi> Mark 16.16.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer; That Faith in Jeſus Chriſt is made the Condition on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151507:17"/>
which all Men muſt be ſaved to whom the Goſpel either was, is, or ever ſhall be preached, is certain; yet as the Goſpel never was appointed to be preached to Infants, as ſuch, neither is it by you, nor any Man in this day; ſo it is not required any where of them to believe in order to their bring ſaved. If it be, who required it? and where? And ſince their natural Capacities is ſuch as renders the work of Believing impoſſible to them (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miracle) whoſe Faith ſhall ſave them, their immediate Parents, nay, rather the Faith of our remote Father, to wit, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam;</hi> as his Unbelief at firſt deſtroyed them, ſo in likelyhood his Faith ſhould intereſs them in the Grace of Eternal Life: but we ſay the Faith of neither; for the Faith and Righteouſneſs of all believing Parents in the World conſidered in one, will not be of Merit ſufficient to ſave one Victim, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14. No, this Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit flows purely from the Fountain of all Grace, and is conveyed to them by another Stream, to wit, God's free and full imputing the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> by whoſe Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Life, and Meritorious Death they are inverted with a Juſtification unto Life Eternal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>As by the offence of one Judgment came upon all Men to Condemnation, even ſo by the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of one, the free Gift came upon all Men unto Juſtification of Life.</hi> Were it ſo that the Faith of Parents did intitle their Children to Salvation, how unworthily would it reflect upon our Lord Jeſus, as if he could not ſave Innocent Babes without their Parents believing, and ſtrongly conclude God to be more prone to Severity then Mercy, in ſaving a very few, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Children of believing Parents, and Eternally damns all the reſt from their Mothers Womb for what they could not help, <hi>viz.</hi> a remote Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinning, and an immediate Fathers not believing; but how contrary is this to that God, whoſe <hi>Mercies are over all his Works,</hi> Pſalm 145.8, 9. So that it's evident the Salvation of dying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants is ſure, though they believe not in the ſence of that Text, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. or with that Faith which alone qualifies a Perſon for Baptiſm. So I come to your</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>Fifth ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>The Children of Believers are ſaid to be holy, this is plainly ſet down in the Text, which cannot be meant, are Legitimate, not Baſtards, for that could not be accounted, if both the Parents had been Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151507:17"/>
neither was that the Queſtion which the Apoſtle here handles. Neither can it be underſtood abſolutely of real holineſs, for then Parents could convey Grace to their Children, and a gracious Man could not have graceleſs Children; but it muſt be meant of foederal Holineſs, as they who were born of the Jews, were Jews not common and unclean as Heathen, but accounted as in the Church, and within the Covenant, ſo that you that are born of Chriſtians, are to be accounted Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, therefore have a right to the Priviledges of Chriſtians. <hi>(2.)</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth explain and confirm this, <hi>Acts 10.15, 28.</hi> and <hi>Rom. 11.16.</hi> if the Root be holy, ſo are the Branches. And it's very obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that of the little that's ſpoke of the caſe of Children in the New Teſtament, all is for it, and not one word againſt it.</p>
               <div n="5" type="answer">
                  <head>Fifth ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>That the Children of Believers are holy, we believe and that their Holineſs is founded upon a better Baſis than the Faith of their immediate Parents; and alſo that it is different from that of their Parents; and ſuch a Holineſs as is ſo far from inright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to Baptiſm, as that till they come to ſin, it doth much rather exempt them: For if Baptiſm be a Sign that ſignifies to all that ſubmit to it, the Remiſſion of Sins, as Scripture ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhews, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. and <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4. &amp;c. then I pray of what uſe can Baptiſm be to thoſe who are under no actual Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Sin, and as ſuch, needs no ſign of Remiſſion of them.</p>
                  <p>But if with <hi>Auſtin,</hi> you ſay, they have Original Sin that muſt be waſht away by Baptiſm, why then their Holineſs before Baptiſm is nothing but Uncleanneſs, agreeable with ſome of your own Coments upon <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.5. <hi>Behold, I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my Mother conceive me.</hi> So that it's plain they have no Holineſs to inright them to Baptiſm, but rather need Baptiſm to make them holy.</p>
                  <p>Further, Conſider how manifeſt a Contradiction the Patrons and Defendors of Pedo-baptiſm meet with from each other, not knowing where to find a ſtay for it's Support. How doth <hi>Auſtin</hi> thwart you; you ſay they that are born of Chriſtians are to be accounted Chriſtians, that is, they are Chriſtians, or ought not to be ſo accompted. And he tells us, as my Author quotes him, in his Book <hi>De Verb. Apoſt. c.</hi> 24.— the Queſtion being, Whether the Infants of baptized Chriſtians were holy? he ſaith Not; becauſe as the Circumciſed begot only the Uncircumciſed,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151507:18"/>
ſo neither did the baptized beget baptized, or (holy ones) the terms are equivolent; the Reaſon he gives, None is new born before he is born. And further proves it by theſe two Illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; (1.) That the pureſt Wheat that is moſt purged from Chaff or Husk, yet being ſown, brings forth Grain that has Chaff and Husk. (2.) That the beſt Grapes that are ſown brings forth wild Grapes. And there is reaſon to believe, that moſt of the Fathers, in this particular, was of <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s mind, as might be gathered from the conſent of whole Councels; take one for all, that is, the <hi>Affrican</hi> Councel, where <hi>Auſtin</hi> was both Preſent and Preſident; they thus Decree:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>All that affirm young Children receive Eternal Life, albeit they be not renewed by Baptiſm, they are accurſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>And notwithſtanding the ſhew of kindneſs you extend to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants in your Coment upon the Text, I am perſwaded you are alſo of <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s mind; for if I miſtake not, in your ſecond Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, you talk as if they muſt be waſhed by Baptiſm; but I tro for what, if they be not unclean, but holy.</p>
                  <p>Further, Every Holineſs gives not a right to Baptiſm. You confeſs the Holineſs in the Text is not a Moral or Real Holineſs, which only oppoſes Sin, Pollution, and Uncleanneſs of Heart and Life; ſo Holineſs is proper only to the Adult. The Veſſels of the Sanctuary are as expreſly ſaid to be holy, as the Children in the Text; ſee 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.19. and <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.28. then ſee how unſound you argue, ſaying, <hi>The Children of Believers are holy;</hi> Ergo, <hi>They ought to be baptized.</hi> The Cups and Veſſels of the Sanctuary are holy; therefore they ought to be baptized. Now to every con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate Man, is not the one Concluſion as truly deducible from the quality, as the other. Who but Men willing to be deceived will conclude any more for the one then for the other? <hi>Auſtin</hi> telling you, whatſoever this Holineſs is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. it is not of power to make Chriſtians, or remit Sins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But you proceed and ſay, It is not Legitimate Holineſs, neither is that the Queſtion that the Apoſtle here handles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Surely Sir you ſhoot at Rovers, and in this have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fooliſhly with your Tongue: Is not Marriage, and Matters relating thereto, the Subject of this whole Chapter? and does the ſcope and deſign of it, beſpeak the Apoſtle labouring the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151507:18"/>
of ſome Doubts and Difficulties that many were under at <hi>Corinth,</hi> that were turned from Idols to God, though but young and weak in the Faith; therefore they write to the Apoſtle for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in Matters and Things they were doubtful of. And what more plain from the manner of the Apoſtle's addreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to them in the firſt Verſe, <hi>Now concerning the things whereof ye write,</hi> &amp;c. One, amongſt others of theſe things, we may rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude was,
<q>
                        <p>Whether a Husband or a Wife, cloſing with Chriſt by Faith, and leaving their Yoke-fellow in Unbelief and Idolatry, might lawfully cleave to them, and cohabit with them, as their true and lawful Yoke-fellows, and as before they did, being both in Unbelief; or whether they muſt not rather leave or diſown them, as to that Relation, becauſe of the ſpiritual difference that is now betwixt them.</p>
                        <p>Now whether this Doubt amongſt them at <hi>Corinth</hi> might ariſe upon their accidental hearing of what God made the Duty of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Reformation in <hi>Ezra</hi>'s and <hi>Nehemiah</hi>'s times, that they ſhould put away their idolatrous Wives, as <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3. I leave.</p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And to the matter propoſed by the <hi>Corinths,</hi> the Apoſtle advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, That the Believer by no means ſhall depart, if in caſe the Unbelieving Party ſtill pleaſe to abide and cohabit with them, as <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12, 13. And further to reſolve them in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, he renders them a twofold Reaſon in the fourteenth <hi>Verſe:</hi> (1.) <hi>The unbelieving Husband is ſanctified by the believing Wife, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving Wife is ſanctified by the believing Husband.</hi> Which is, as if he had ſaid, You are as truly Man and Wife in God's account now as you were before; your Marriage as honourable, your Bed as undefiled, your living and lying together as unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the ſight of God as ever; the Husband and Wife as truly ſanctified a Companion for each other, notwithſtanding the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between them in Matters of Religion; which the Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator on this Text, in the Second Volume of Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Work, ſaith, <hi>The Believer, without Offence to the Law of God, may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in a married ſtate with ſuch a Yoke-fellow, notwithſtanding their diſpoſition in Matters of Faith.</hi> And <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> with others, tell us expreſly, <hi>That Children are legitimately holy;</hi> agreeable with that
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151507:19"/>
in <hi>Malachy</hi> 2.15. where the Lord himſelf calls the Children born in lawful Marriage a <hi>godly Seed.</hi> Therefore as a (2.) Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, the Apoſtle removes the Abſurdity that the ſcrupulous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts at <hi>Corinth</hi> feared, ſaying, <hi>Elſe were your Children unclean, but now are they holy:</hi> i. e. Were it ſo as you fear, that deſpari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Matters of Religion diſſolved the Marriage Bond, why then your Iſſue would be born in Uncleanneſs, and bear the Blot of Baſtardy upon them. But to remove this Scruple, and ſatisfie that there abode is as warrantable as ever, ſaith elſewhere, <hi>Your Children were unclean, but now are they holy.</hi> Now as the Husband and Wife are ſanctified to each other, abiding in that honourable, or holy ſtate of Matrimony, the Children born unto them are holy, which needs no longer to be feared by you, as Holineſs and Sanctification oppoſeth the Uncleanneſs of Fornication, 1 <hi>Theſs.</hi> 4.3, 5.</p>
                  <p>Now I pray, Sir, if this be not the Queſtion that the Apoſtle here handles, will you ſhew us what it is, or ceaſe to darken Counſel by words without knowledge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You proceed, and muſt needs have this to be Foederal Holineſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining it thus, As they that were born of the Jews, were Jews, not common and unclean as Heathen, but accounted as in the Church, ſo that you, that are born of Chriſtians, are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> The Heathen were bad enough, is granted, and that you need not make them worſe, believing you will never be able to prove the difference ſo great between the Iſſue of Jews and Gentiles, that had an equal advantage of being born of Parents that were lawfully married, what degree of Sanctity deſcended upon the Jews in lawful Marriage, more then upon the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of the Gentiles under the ſame Circumſtance, I know not; and yet I believe <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a People bleſt with an Eminent Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs above the Gentile Nations in common. But then, that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Holineſs ſtreamed to them from another Fountain than meerly being born of the Jews in holy Matrimony, to wit, the Grace and Love of God, in that he was pleaſed to chooſe them, before any other Nation, to make them his People, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly bleſt them with holy Laws and Ordinances, as <hi>Pſalm</hi> 147.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151507:19"/>That every one born of Jewiſh Parents was a Jew, is not doubted, but that the Jews were Church Members by their Birth, is not ſo eaſie; for if they were Church Members ſo ſoon as born, they had a right (I conceive) to the Priviledges thereof. But with reſpect to the Paſſover, we are expreſly told, that no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed Perſon ſhall eat thereof, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. And that ſuch as are born to you <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, are <hi>Engliſh</hi> men, and ſo account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though born in <hi>France, Spain,</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi> where ſuch born of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parents, even diſdain to be accounted but <hi>Engliſh;</hi> but that ſuch as are born of Chriſtians, are Chriſtians, is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radox, and abſurd with a witneſs, conſidering that no leſs then a believing the Doctrine, and an imitation of the Life and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Chriſt, can truly denominate a Man to be a Chriſtian. At this rate, a Man that is an Idolater begets an Idolater, and an Hypocrite begets an Hypocrite. Strange Divinity!</p>
                  <p>And as to the Text you cite, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.16. it favours not your Concluſion at all, for if by <hi>Firſt-fruits</hi> and <hi>Root,</hi> you will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe holy Perſons <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> yet its evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent the whole Lump and Branches were not ſo, by their manifeſt rejecting the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for amongſt whom did he meet with more notorious Enemies then amongſt the Jews: Did their tempting, belying, betraying, accuſing, condemning, and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Lord of Life, beſpeak them to be a holy Lump, which in your ſence they muſt be, as they proceeded from a <hi>holy Root,</hi> to wit, <hi>Abraham,</hi> notwithſtanding the many Inſolencies and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignities wherewith they treated the Lord Jeſus. How directly oppoſite is this to what Chriſt ſaith of the Jews, the natural Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who notwithſtanding that, tells them, <hi>That they were of their Father the Devil,</hi> John 8.44.</p>
                  <p>But by that Scripture we may underſtand, that as God did look favourably on <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Root of that People, ſo alſo he doth favour the Branches of that whole Nation that ſprang from him, and therefore as ſome of the Jews had received Chriſt, and were thereby intereſted in the Divine Favour, ſo the words rightly underſtood are an Incouragement to the Unbelieving Jews that ſtand of, to come into Chriſt, aſſuring them thereupon, that he would not reject them, but take them into his Favour, as Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es that proceeded from ſo holy a Root; they alſo contain an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to take off the Gentiles that were come in, from judging and cenſuring the Jews upon their Rejection, and being Caſt off;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151507:20"/>
for though God in Juſtice hath cut off the obdurate Jew, and graciouſly taken in the Gentiles through believing, yet from that favour he anciently bore towards that People, he will not have the Gentiles to deſpiſe them, who is ready to receive them into favour as Branches ſpringing from ſo holy a Root, if they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued not in Infidelity, which is evident in this and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Verſes; ſo that all the Scripture ſpeaks of Infants right to Baptiſm, whether more or leſs, or nothing at all, it's evident you have ſaid nothing to purpoſe from it. I paſs to your</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>Sixth ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>What hinders but that the Children of profeſſing Believers may be baptized? Nothing on God's part; who hath declared himſelf ready to receive them, and take them into Covenant, together with their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſaid, That of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven; nothing in the Sacrament, they may have all that is eſſential unto Baptiſm gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them, as well as to Adult grown Perſons; nothing on the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters part, but they may baptize Infants as well as grown Perſons; and nothing on the Childrens part, as hath been ſhewn; they are capable of it, and have a right unto it, as they were capable of Circumciſion, and had a right to it.</p>
               <div n="6" type="answer">
                  <head>Sixth ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>As to the firſt of what is contain'd in this Argument, of their being taken into Covenant, and belonging to the Kingdom of Heaven, is ſufficiently ſpoke to already, in my Anſwers to your Second and Fourth Arguments: A word or two to the Quereſt, demanding what hinders. Methinks this Queſtion is ſo fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by the Holy Ghoſt in that Eighth of the <hi>Acts, verſes</hi> 36, 37. that no thinking Man could, without bluſhing, have ſo interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated. However, if you are willing to know, I will tell you, and amongſt many things, there is one that may warrantably hinder, and that is a total want of Command from God for your Authority; could you once preface your practice with a <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> every Mouth would be ſtopped; but till then, we humbly deſire, <hi>who hath required this at your hands,</hi> it may be worthy your ſearch; for ſure that which God never had a will
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151507:20"/>
to require, he will never have a heart to accept: if things but half done in purſuance to his Command, be a rejecting his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, as in the Caſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> how much more a doing things in his Name to which he never directed: If the Lord delights not in the Burnt-offerings and Sacrifices he once required, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively to an obeying his Voice, how much leſs will he delight in Works of Supererogation, in things done over and above in what he hath commanded. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22, 23. But if you aſſign the Commiſſion of Chriſt for your warrant, is it not plain from thence, that you have broke his Law, and changed his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and that at beſt you do but one thing for another, which is not one jot the better; for this cauſe the Earth is defiled, and the Land mourneth; for truly may the Lord ſay, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 24 5. <hi>They have tranſgreſſed my Laws, and changed my Ordinances.</hi> Sir, That an expreſs Command is neceſſary for the warranting your practice, is no more then what you have acknowledged, <hi>(viz.) That it is the Command of God only that can conſtitute an Ordinance of God,</hi> which you affirm your ſprinkling of Infants to be; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſign your Command, as you would the Lord ſhould not ſay of you, as of others in another Caſe, <hi>They have done that which I commanded them not, neither came it into my heart,</hi> Jer. 7.31. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will you ever be able to quit your ſelves from the Guilt of Will-worſhip, which we juſtly charge upon you; which truly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd, is, as I ſhall give it you from the worthy Doctor <hi>Hopkin,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>London Derry,</hi> as I find it in his Expoſition upon the Ten Commandments, (worthy to be printed in Letters of Gold) <hi>page</hi> 142. who ſays,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Will-worſhip is nothing elſe but an inventing and aſcribing any other Worſhip unto God, beſides what he hath been pleaſed to Command and Inſtitute. God ſaith,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Will worſhip, what it is.</note> 
                     <hi>he will not be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped according to our Fancies, but his own Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for as we muſt have no other God beſides the true, ſo that God muſt have no other Service performed unto him, beſides what himſelf hath required and preſcribed; for this were to impute folly and weakneſs unto him, as if indeed he would have Servants, but knew not what Service to injoyn them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And by this time I hope you may ſee what may hinder, if not, may not I as induſtriouſly inquire why <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> might not bring ſtrange Fire to the Lord's Altar, I know of no expreſs Command of God hindering, and yet for their unadviſed at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151507:21"/>
the Lord ſends Fire from Heaven and deſtroys them both, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2. Let us therefore fear to do any thing in the Worſhip of God which he hath not commanded, nor conclude our ſelves ſafe, though he hath not in ſo many expreſs words forbid it. To do what he hath commanded is our work, not what he hath not prohibited, elſe where would our wild Inventions terminate.</p>
                  <p>Further, If this be not ſufficient to hinder, I pray what may hinder your uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm; Is that Ceremony any more incongruous to holy Writ then your own practice? And why find you fault with the Church of <hi>England</hi> for the uſe of their Ceremonies, whereas many of them are ſo indifferent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that for ought I know they may, or may not be uſed. Nay, if any thing can warrant you, ſhort of a Command of God, to ſet up this or that in the Worſhip of God, as an Ordinance of God, may not the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> pretend to as good Authority for any part of their practice that is not in ſo many expreſs words forbid, eſpecially their Baptizing with Salt and Spittle, as you can for yours. I do ſincerely profeſs, were I ſatisfied that either Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom or Conſequence were a warrant ſufficient to bear you out in this particular, I ſhould reckon my diſſenting from the Church of <hi>England</hi> (where I may be as holy as I will or can) might be juſtly imputed to my Ignorance or Peviſhneſs.</p>
                  <p>You add, <hi>Nothing in the Sacrament may hinder, they may have all that is Eſſential to Baptiſm given to them, as well as the Adult and grown Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Sir, It is ſtrange that you ſhould ſo thwart your own practice; for I preſume there is not any whom you Baptize, but you do it upon a Profeſſion of Faith, if not their own, yet their Parents; ſo that your own practice beſpeaks Faith eſſential. And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his <hi>Poor Man's Family Book, pag.</hi> 168. affirmeth, <hi>The Church never knew any Baptiſm, but ſuch as was joyned with a preſent profeſſion of preſent Faith and Repentance, and Renunciation of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, the World, and the Fleſh, and a total devotedneſs to God in Chriſt.</hi> Alſo the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her Catechiſm, to this Queſtion, <hi>What is required of Perſons to be baptized?</hi> The Anſwer is, <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, whereby they forſake ſin, and Faith, whereby they ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</hi> Which, with <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. is evident that Repentance, Faith and devotedneſs to God is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151507:21"/>
but how doth it appear that Children are capable of theſe things? When did any Child give you the leaſt Evidence that he Believed, Repented, Renounced the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil? and that before he can poſſibly know the nature, or evil, of the one, or the other. Remember, Sir, that which appears not, is not; nor let it ſuffice that the Parent believes for the Child: for I pray, why may not the Parents Baptiſm paſs currant for the Child, as the Parents Faith.</p>
                  <p>You add, <hi>Nothing on the Miniſter's part, but they may Baptize Infants as well as grown Perſons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> I confeſs ſome Miniſters by permiſſion, and through the liberty of their own will, may do what they pleaſe; but in that caſe, what they do is neither in obedience to any Command of Chriſt, nor in Imitation to any Example of the Apoſtles, who neither did, nor durſt do it, but had it been in their liberty, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controverſie they had done it, and then their preſident had been ſufficient. But though <hi>Paul</hi> ſhunned not to declare unto the Elders and Churches the whole Counſel of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27. yet the Baptizing of Infants no where appears, to be either any part of the Lord's Counſel, or his Miniſters Practice; therefore as you would have a comfortable Evidence that you are the Lord's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, it becomes you publickly to enter your Proteſt againſt this practice for the undeceiving of many; and for the future, that you preſume to do nothing in his Name, but what you have his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for.</p>
                  <p>You ſay further, <hi>There is nothing on the Childrens part, as hath been ſhewn,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> As hath been ſhewn there is nothing on the Childrens part that renders it needful; and as they need it not, ſo they have not the leaſt appearance of right to it.</p>
                  <p>As to their Capacity, being the ſame with them that received Circumciſion, I conceive it to be a wide miſtake; for they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved both Capacity and Right for Circumciſion from the words of Inſtitution, and not becauſe they were either able or unable imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to anſwer the Obligation they were laid under by it, which was to <hi>keep the whole Law,</hi> Gal. 5.3. Therefore, as your
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151507:22"/>
Infants now are able to do no more then they did under the Law, and you having no Inſtitution and Divine Authority for your war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, beſpeaks both their incapacity and want of right; but as to your Females, I perceive they have both a larger Capacity and Propriety than thoſe of old, in that yours muſt be baptized, though the others were never circumciſed. I paſs to your</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>Seventh ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>I may add, That the practice of the Church of Chriſt, both primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and modern, is a good Comment on all theſe Texts, and though it is not the Foundation we build this Doctrine upon, yet it may help to ſtrengthen and confirm us in the belief of it in dark and difficult Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; eſpecially we ſhould have regard what hath been the Stream and Currant of the godly Learned in all Ages, the way of good Men, for wiſe Men to walk in. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith, That for his part he cannot find in his ſmall reading, that any one Divine, or party of Men, did certainly oppoſe or deny Infant Baptiſm for many hundred years after Chriſt; and adds, that you cannot prove ſo much as one Man, except one <hi>Herimarus,</hi> that did once oppoſe or deny Infant Baptiſm, from the Apoſtles days till about <hi>Luther</hi>'s time; but I could quote you <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Origen, Jerom, Cyprian,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the great Lights of the Church, all for it.</p>
               <div n="7" type="answer">
                  <head>Seventh ANSWER.</head>
                  <p>You are pleaſed, I perceive, to reſtrain the Churches of Chriſt to the conventions of your own practice, and to exclude all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering with you in the point of Baptiſm; ſo that many Churches, as perſpicuous as your ſelves, eſpecially in a trying ſeaſon, have little thanks to give you for your Charity towards them: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſince you make not the practice of preceding Churches the Baſis on which you build, only call them in for Light and Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to help you in Caſes dark and difficult, as by your own Grant, as well as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s, That the Baptizing of Infants is, if it be an Ordinance at all, it is next to a Miracle, that all the famous Lights ſhining in the Churches, have not given ſo much light and clearneſs in this thing of ſo much weight and moment, but that it ſhould ſtill be found ſo dark and difficult, as it appears
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151507:22"/>
to this day; and when a Star will ariſe to make it more clear then it is, I know not.</p>
                  <p>But in fine, to perſwade your Brethren into a good and firm opinion of it, you tell them that you could quote <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Origin, Cyprian, Jerom,</hi> and S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> all for it; to tell them you can do it, is much eaſier than to do it: And to tell you by the way, if you have read the Fathers, you know in your Conſcience, that though ſome baptized Infants in the Third and Fourth Centuries, for particular ends, yet none in thoſe Ages practiſed Infant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm as a Goſpel Ordinance, if any before <hi>Auſtin,</hi> as may be ſhewed from Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Teſtimony, with others. Therefore to come to a Concluſion, though I might give Inſtances at large from <hi>Tertullian,</hi> with all, or moſt of thoſe you name, together with <hi>Nazianzene, Ambroſe, Athanaſius,</hi> and many more, as they are handed to me, all bearing head ſtrongly againſt your practice; yet take one for all, which ſways much with me, as I find it quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and you may read it in this order of words in his <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt, pag.</hi> 143. <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the primitive times none were baptized without an expreſs Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting, wherein they renounced the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, and ingage themſelves to Chriſt, as you may ſee,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in</hi> Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Origen, <hi>and</hi> Cyprian, <hi>and others at large.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, Sir, I would ask you, whether Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> never read of any that oppoſed Infant Baptiſm; whereas he tells you, That none of old were baptized without an expreſs Covenanting. Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you have either miſ-quoted Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> or elſe he greatly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got himſelf when he ſaid as you ſpeak of him; yea, he proceeds and names <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in particular in the ſame Book and Page, ſpeaking of the order and manner of baptizing the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and how we are dedicated to God, being renewed by Chriſt, ſaith he, we will now open unto you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As many as being perſwaded do believe theſe things to be true which we teach, and do promiſe to live according to them; they firſt learn by Prayer and Faſting to beg pardon of God for their former ſins, our ſelves joyning alſo our Prayer and Faſting; then they are brought to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and born again (or baptized) in the ſame way as our ſelves were born again; for they are waſhed in water in the Name of the Father, the Lord and God of all, and of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Holy Ghoſt. Then we bring the Perſon thus waſhed and inſtructed to the Brethren, as they are called, where the Aſſemblies are, that we may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151507:23"/>
pray both for our ſelves and the illuminated Perſon, that we may be found by true Doctrine and by good Works worthy obſervers and keepers of the Commandments, and that we may obtain Eternal Salvation. Then there is brought to the chief Brother, ſo they called the chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Bread and a Cup of Wine, waſhed, which taking, he offereth Praiſe and Thanksgiving to the Father, by the Name of the Son and Holy Ghoſt; and ſo a while he celebrateth Thanksgiving; and after Prayer the whole Aſſembly ſaith</hi> Amen. <hi>Thanksgiving being ended, by the Preſident or chief Guide, and the conſent of the whole People, the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, as we call them, do give to every one preſent part of the Bread and Wine, over which Thanks was given, and they alſo ſuffer them to bring it to the abſent; this Food we alſo call the</hi> Euchariſt; <hi>to which no Man is admitted but only he which believeth the truth of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, being waſhed in the Laver of Regeneration for remiſſion of ſins, and that ſo liveth as Chriſt hath taught. This then,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Baxter, is no new and over ſtrict way, you ſee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus I have done with your ſeven Arguments, believing (through the Mercy of God) might what is ſaid be impartially conſidered, be ſufficient to bring us to that Unity of Judgment in all the Truths of Jeſus Chriſt, and Conformity in Practice that might render us more ſerviceable in carrying on that Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in the World for our One and Only Lord, which would be mighty conduceable to his Glory, and a full Evidence, through Grace, of our own Title to that Glory which ſhortly will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in him, unto whom be given all Glory in the Church throughout all Ages, Even ſo. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>An APPENDIX. Seven Arguments ſhewing that Infants ought not to be Baptized.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Firſt Argument.</label> IF Chriſt in the Commiſſion <hi>Matth 28.19.</hi> commands his Diſciples to baptize none, but the very fame perſons he commanded them alſo firſt to teach, and make Diſciples by teaching, then that place is a plain prohibition, and not a precept to baptize Infants, for Men cannot teach or diſciple Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:151507:23"/>But Chriſt there commands his Diſciples to baptize none but ſuch as he commands them alſo, firſt to teach and make Diſciples by teaching, therefore that place is a plain prohibition, and not at all a precept to baptize Infants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If it be required, we ſhall give you proof enough hereof out of your own Authors, as well as others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Second Argument.</label> 
               <hi>If Infants ought to be baptized, then Infant Baptiſm is of Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; but Infant Baptiſm is not of Divine Inſtitution, therefore they ought not to be baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Major is true, if as you ſay there is but one Command for Baptiſm, <hi>viz Matth.</hi> 28.19. which appears by the fore-going Argument to be a plain prohibition of Infant Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>The Minor is true, becauſe no Man can ſhew any Inſtitution of Infant Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Third Argument.</label> If Infants ought to be baptized as agreeable with the Command of Chriſt, then it is agreeable to the practice of the Apoſtolical Churches; but Infant Baptiſm is not agreeable to the practice of the Apoſtolical Churches, therefore Infants ought not to be bapized as agreeable to the Command of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Major is true, becauſe the Apoſtolical Church did obſerve</hi> T.G. <hi>all that Chriſt commanded in the Caſe of Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Minor is true, becauſe no Man can ſhew that the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Churches did Baptize ſo much as one Infant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Fourth Argument.</label> 
               <hi>If Infants ought to be Baptized, then Infant Baptiſm is a part of Divine Worſhip, either natural or poſitive; but Infant Baptiſm is no part of Divine Worſhip, either natural or poſitive, therefore they ought not to be baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Major is true by your own grant, that Infant Baptiſm is an Ordinance of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Minor appears thus; If it be any part of Natural Worſhip, it is to be found either among the Heathen that have not the Law, or certainly among the Patriarchs who were before the Law.—</p>
            <p>But it hath not been known to either of them.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151507:24"/>(2) If it be a part of Poſitive Worſhip, then it becomes ſo by Precept and Command, but there is no Command, if there be aſſign it.</p>
            <p>Note, All Commands are either Expreſs or Implicite: An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Command requires the performance of it; an Implicite Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhews that ſome have been commended in the practice of it, or blamed in the neglect of it; but you can ſhew neither.</p>
            <p>I ſhall take leave to wave a term, and ſo turn the edge of Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Sword againſt you, in my fifth and ſixth Arguments, which I find in his <hi>Plain Scripture Proof, falſly ſo called,</hi> p. 130.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Fifth Argument.</label> That practice which goeth upon meer uncertainty, and hath no Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rule to guide it, is not according to the will of Chriſt; but the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of baptizing Infants goes upon mear uncertainty, and hath no Rule in Scripture to guide it, therefore its not according to the will of Chriſt, nor ought Infants to be baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Sixth Argument.</label> That practice which doth neceſſarily fill the Church with perpetual Contention, as being about a matter that cannot be determined by any known Rule, is not according to the mind of Chriſt: But the practice of baptizing Infants is ſuch as will neceſſarily fill the Church with perpetual Contention, as that which cannot be determined by any known Rule, therefore it is not according to the mind of Chriſt; nor ought In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants to be baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Seventh Argument.</label> 
               <hi>That practice which renders the practice of Chriſt, and his true Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, who were baptized in Rivers (or much water) ſuperfluous or ridiculous, and which agreeth not with the word</hi> Baptize, <hi>when uſed in the</hi> New Teſtament <hi>to expreſs the act done, in that Ordinance, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Command of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the ſprinkling of Infants now uſed by you, renders the practice of Chriſt, and his true Followers, who were baptized in Rivers, or much Water, ſuperfluous or ridiculous, and agreeth not with the ſignification of the word</hi> Baptize, <hi>when uſed to expreſs, according to the</hi> New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>the act done in that Ordinance; therefore Infant Baptiſm is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Command of Chriſt, and ought not to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:151507:24"/>The Major is true, becauſe Chriſt hath Commanded nothing that reflects diſhonour upon his own practice. —The <hi>T.G.</hi> Minor is true, becauſe if Sprinkling a little Water upon the Face only be ſufficient, then Immerſion or Dipping in the River muſt needs be ſuperfluous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Neither can the word <hi>Baptize</hi> and <hi>Rantiſe,</hi> with any equity of Speech or good Senſe, be uſed to expreſs the ſame Action.</p>
            <p>Now how poor and paultry ſoever our Arguments againſt your practice, as you term them, may be, I leave to conſideration, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe ſufficient to juſtifie all in refuſing Infant Baptiſm; and if poſſible, to perſwade you more effectually to endeavour the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this Ordinance to its priſtine Purity, in which you will do well: And ſo Farewel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <head>
               <hi>The CONCLUSION.</hi> Being a Word to my Brethren of the Baptized CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCHES.</head>
            <p>INto whoſe of your hands ſoever theſe Lines may come, with them I greet you in the Lord, through whom, from God the Father, I ſincerely wiſh you an increaſe of all Grace and Peace, praying that you may keep your ſelves in the love of God, and in a patient waiting for the coming of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And that we may be without blame in that day, let us in this day, Brethren, conſider our Calling, and the Obligation we are laid for ever under, by that Grace which God through Chriſt hath ſo freely and fully imparted unto us, ſo as that every one of us may fill up our places in the Church of God, adorning the Truth which we profeſs, as it is in Jeſus, ordering the affairs of our whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations with circumſpection, expreſſing Piety flowing from hearts ſincere towards God, and Humility, Love, and Reverence towards all Men, in all things, a defect in either of theſe may juſtly make way for a, <hi>What do ye more then others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without controverſie, if any People in the World have the true Form of Godlineſs, you have; and in holding faſt the Form of ſound words, ye do well, but better in making manifeſt the Power
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151507:25"/>
of Godlineſs, without which the true Form will not avail, but turn to our detriment. I deſign not to impeach any of you, though I would to God there were no cauſe; but earneſtly perſwade to a more compleat and conſtant Conformity to Chriſt our Head, not only in Doctrine but in Imitation, that Holineſs, with the Fear and Favour of God, may fill our Aſſemblies and Houſes to their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Borders, and our Hearts being fill'd with Love thereto, we may at all times, by good Converſations, ſhew forth our <hi>works with meekneſs of Wiſdom,</hi> James 3.13. This would certainly render Arguments for Truth more powerful and convincing, and atract and win upon the hearts of the more conſiderate and wiſe, though not one with us in holy Baptiſm; whenas Prophaneneſs, Folly, and Uncharitableneſs in <hi>Iſrael</hi> will diſ-ingage and harden more than a whole Volume of the moſt pregnant and invincible Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will make to yield. Therefore, Brethren, as we are called to Holineſs, let us expreſſively evidence, that what we know of God in Chriſt, is more than ſpeculative. And to that end,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Be ready unto every good Work that refers to your Duty to God, in that relation you ſtand in to the Church of God.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Be truly generous and wiſe in your deportment towards all Men, eſpecially the more Sober and Religious; avoid Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Unwarrantable Judging of ſuch; treat them in love, as Brethren, and occaſionally, as you have opportunity, contend earneſtly for the Truth, yet without heat and paſſion. Maintain your Communion intire, and Separation compleat from all whoſe fear, more or leſs, in the Worſhip of God, is taught by the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of Men, and not after the Traditions given us by Chriſt and his Apoſtles; yet in all things wherein we are agreed, let us walk, uniting in Affection, till God ſhall reveal the reſt unto them, praying earneſtly that God would cauſe the Beams of Goſpel Light powerfully to dart into the Minds of all, helping them by Divine Illumination to diſcern Truth's ſhining Beauty and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that all Error may fall before it, as <hi>Dagon</hi> did before the Ark, and that none may find either heart or hand to ſupport it, that Chriſt's own Fold may be filled with his own Sheep in this our day; yea, through the Increaſe of Knowledge and Righteouſneſs, let Honour and Glory be given to the Lamb, and all the Earth know that the Lord alone is God. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151507:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
